Isabel Howland Papers, 1888-1903
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Isabel Howland papers
1888-1903
Howland, Isabel, 1859-1942
MS 78
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Suffragist and social Reformer. Papers consist of correspondence plus other materials related to her position as corresponding secretary of the Association for the Advancement of Women and of the New York State Woman Suffrage Association. Subjects include women's suffrage, women's rights, and other reform movements such as temperance and anti-slavery.
Isabel Howland was born to a Quaker family in Sherwood, New York in 1859. She earned a B.A. from Cornell University in 1881. The niece of suffragist, abolitionist and educator Emily Howland, Isabel was involved in similar causes. She was corresponding secretary of the Association for the Advancement of Women in the 1880s and involved in the New York State Woman Suffrage Association. From 1884 to 1885, she accompanied her aunt Emily Howland on European travels. She lived in Paris for much of the 1930s to care for her invalid brother, Herbert. She died in 1942.
The Isabel Howland Papers date from 1888 to 1903 and consist mainly of correspondence plus other materials related to her position as corresponding secretary of the Association for the Advancement of Women and of the New York State Woman Suffrage Association. Subjects include women's suffrage, women's rights, and other reform movements such as temperance and the battle for the abolition of slavery. Notable correspondents include Susan B. Anthony, Alida Avery, Alice Stone Blackwell, Carrie Chapman Catt, William Lloyd Garrison, Adele Hutchinson, Anna Howard Shaw, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Lucy Stone, Booker T. Washington, Frances E. Willard, and Julia Ward Howe.
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Biographical Information
II. Correspondence
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Isabel Howland Papers were obtained by purchase.
Search Terms
Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906--Correspondence; Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950--Correspondence; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947--Correspondence; Garrison, William Lloyd, 1805-1879--Correspondence; Howe, Julia Ward, 1819-1910--Correspondence; Howland, Emily, 1827-1929; Howland, Isabel; Shaw, Anna Howard, 1847-1919--Correspondence; Stanton, Elizabeth Cady, 1815-1902--Correspondence; Stone, Lucy, 1818-1893--Correspondence; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915--Correspondence; Willard, Frances Elizabeth, 1839-1898--Correspondence; Association for the Advancement of Women--History--Sources; Antislavery movements--United States--History--Sources; New York State Woman Suffrage Association--History--Sources; Abolitionists--United States--History--19th century--Sources; Suffragists--United States--Correspondence; Women--Suffrage--United States--History--19th century--Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Memorabilia, 1888-98, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Microfilm reel guide to Emily Howland Papers at Cornell University (Box 1)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (to Isabel Howland unless otherwise noted)
  - Anthony, Lucy and Mary, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthony, Susan B., 1892-1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aikens, Amanda L., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anagnos, Michael, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Avery, Alida C., 1888-90 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Avery, Susan Look (also to M. Jacobs), 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Babcock, Elnora M., 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bagg, Mary E., 1889-90 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barnes, Catherine Weed, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Barrows, Isabel C., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bates, Octavia W., 1891-94 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Benson, Louise, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1890-97 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Blackwell, Antoinette Brown, 1889-91 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blackwell, Henry B., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Blackwell, Sarah Ellen, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boole, Ella A. to Mrs. L.G. Robinson, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Booth, Mary A., 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bouland, Clara, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bowser, Anna C. (also to M. Jacobs), 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bray, Maria H. to Miss Peckham, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brown, Charlotte Emerson, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Campbell, Helen, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cardwill, Mary E., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Carmichael, Margaret, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Catt, Carrie Chapman to Emily Howland (aunt of Isabel), 1895-96, 1901-03, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Catt, Carrie Chapman to Mrs. Hannah L. Howland, 1896, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Chapin, A.J., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cheney, Ednah Dow (also to M. Jacobs), 1889 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Clapp, Romelia L., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cobb, Mary E.R., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Colby, Clara B. (includes photograph), 1892-99 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Comstock, Anne, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Conway, Clara (also to Julia Ward Howe), 1890 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Croly, Jane Cunningham to Julia W. Howe, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Curtis, Elizabeth Burrill, 1894, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dickenson, M.L., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dietrick, Ellen B., 1891, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dodge, Grace H., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Donlevy, Alice, 1887-88 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Easby, Gertrude K., 1891 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Eastman, Annis Ford, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Eastman, Mary E., 1889-92 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Eddy, Sarah, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Edwards, Louise, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Elliott, Maud Howe, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Erol, Helen G., 1894 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Fairchild, S., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Fleming, Jennie to Mrs. Hamilton, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Fletcher, Alice C., 1890 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Franklin, C. Ladd, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - French, Annie D., 1888-90 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Frisbee, E.S., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Gage, Matilda Joslyn, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Galt, Eleanor, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Gannett, M.T. Lewis, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Garrison, Francis J.,1892 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Garrison, William Lloyd (II), 1895 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gleason, Rachael, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Greenleaf, Jean Brooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Gregg, David, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Grew, Mary, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Grubbs, S.J., 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Hale, Edward Everett, 1891, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Hale, Lucretia P., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Hallowell, Sarah C.F., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Hamilton, Henrietta, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Hazard, Rebecca, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Hoffman, Sophia C., 1890-91 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Howe, Julia Ward, 1888-94, undated (Box 1, Folder 73-74)
  - Howell, Mary Seymour, 1892, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Howland, Herbert, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Hufford, Lois G. to A.B. Blackwell, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hultin, Ida C. to M. Jacobs, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Huntington, Anna S., undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Hutchinson, Adele S.,1891-92 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Irving, Carrie E.S., 1895 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Jenkins, Helen, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Kennard, Caroline A.,1889-90 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Kirk, Eleanor, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Landen, Jean M., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Lapham, Ella C., 1888-90 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lawler, Fanny, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lazenby, William R., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Leonard, Georgia L., 1890-91 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Love, Alfred H., 1889, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lowell, Josephine Shaw, 1889, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lozier, Jennie, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McCowen, Dr. Jennie, 1890-91 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - McGillvray, Alice, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mark, Nellie V., 1890-91, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Merrell, Ina B., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Meyer, Annie Nathan, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Miller, Olive, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mills, Charles De B., 1889, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mills, Harriet May, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mitchell, Ellen, 1891-92 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mittermair, Dr. Wolfgang, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Moore, Sarah Wool, 1889-92 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mowry, Martha H. (also to M. Jacobs), 1890 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Newton, Mary A., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Noble, Lydia, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Parker, Frank Stuart, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Parks, Isabella W., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Peck, Annie S., 1892, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Peckham, Mary C. (also to Mrs. Hazard), 1889 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Perry, Belle S., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Phelps, Minnie L. to Mrs. Peckham, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pierce, Charlotte L., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pillsbury, Parker to Miss Putnam, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rich, Ellen W., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Ripley, Mary A., 1889-92 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rockwell, Kate W., 1889 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Roe, J.E., undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Rogers, Mary F., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Rogers, May, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sargent, Ellen W., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sayles, Lita B., undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sayles, Lita B., 1888-91 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Shurman, J.G., 1892-93 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Searing (?), A., 1894, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Searls, W., 1888 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Severance, Caroline, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sewall, May Wright, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Shaw, Anna Howard to Emily Howland, 1903-10, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Shaw, Dr. Anna Howard, 1899, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Shield, Helen S., 1889 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Skinner, M.P., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Slocum, Jane M., 1899 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Smiley, Louise M., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Smith, Hannah W.. 1888 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Smith, Lucy W.1888 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Snow, B.B., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Soper, Grace, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Spear, C.S. Brown to M. Jacobs, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Stebbins, Catherine, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Stevenson, T.E. to M.C. Peckham, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Stone, Lucy, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Stowe, Emily to M. Jacobs, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Sunderland, Eliza, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Talbot, Marion, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Tappan, Eva March, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Thomas, Elizabeth, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Thomas, Martha Carey, 1885, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Thorne, Elizabeth F. to Margaret Grierson about E.H. and I.H., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Tifft, E. Amelia, 1890, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Tifft, Elizabeth Lord, 1891, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Townsend, Harriet A., 1890-94 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Unidentified, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Walters, Albertine S. to A.A.W., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Wanamaker, John, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Warner, Helen G., 1898 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Washington, Booker T., 1897 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Wells, Kate Gannett, 1888-91, undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Wendell, Caroline R., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Wentworth, S.E., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Wetherald, Ethelyn, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Whiting, Lilian, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Wilcox, B.M., 1895 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Wilde, Catherine, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Willard, Frances E., 1887-88, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Williams, Charlotte to M.C. Peckham, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Wing, Mary E., 1888-89 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Ward, Frances Fisher, 1890-91 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Wolcott, H.L.T., 1890-91 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Woods, Kate T., 1889-90 (Box 2, Folder 86)